[Music]
Stanford
University I'm going to do something now
I've wanted to do for years I I really
wanted to do this
okay ladies and Gentlemen people out in
the audience viewing this from afar
we're now going to stop for a commercial
break I want you all to go out and buy
my book
the black hole
War my battle with Steven Hawking to
make the world safe for quantum
mechanics in that book you will learn
about the cruelty of theoretical
physicists you will not only learn about
Schrodinger's cat but you will learn
about ssin's fish and how he flushed
them down the
toilet audience please yeah yeah yeah
come on
all right now back to our program you
may remember that when we last Saw Alice
and Bob Alice was crying
bitterly because the cruel Bob was
forcing her to learn group
Theory Alice sad to say is not finished
Bob is not finished with
her theight
tonight we will see Alice
suffer
more okay are there any questions about
uh group theory for the moment that
uh now that we're back to the story main
story line any any questions about group
Theory we're gon to we're not finished
with it we're really not finished with
it um
yeah there's there's two parts of your
expose on group it seems to be some kind
of abstract mathematical object that has
some kind of multiplication table and
there's also the part on how those
groups act on various
objects right can we dissociate the two
or is it well
they they're completely related there's
the abstract notion Let's uh let's take
the case of rotation of a
spin right there's a perfect case to to
study there's the abstract completely
abstract notion of a rotation in space
and I don't tell you what it acts on I
just tell you that is an operation that
you can
do
physics has to respect the Symmetry
under the rotations of uh of space right
and so we must then say how does the
rotation of
space act on the Quant ities which
describe which are physically relevant
right if we were talking about classical
physics we might just say that the
rotation of space uh rotates the
coordinates of a particle it might
rotate the direction of a magnet
whatever it does we know how to describe
that we describe that by well we know
how to how to describe
that in quantum mechanics the states of
a system are always represented by a
linear Vector space
face there's the abstract notion of a
state of a system and there's the
concrete representation of it in terms
of column vectors how big are those
column vectors what's the what's the
number of entries into the column Vector
well that depends on the system but
basically it's the number of mutually
orthogonal
possibilities for that system if the
system in question only consists of an
electron spin then there's only two
states two mutually orthogonal States
spin up spin down if it's two electrons
and again we're only interested in the
spin then there would be four states two
up two down one up one down one down one
up uh if we're talking about a more
complex object for example the entire
motion of an electron its position as
well as its momentum then there are an
infinite number of states the number of
states that it takes to describe the or
orbital loc uh the number of mutually
orthogonal
states of an
electron speaking now about its position
is infinite it could be anywhere's in
space or you could choose to describe it
in terms of
momentum so the column vectors
describing an electron's
position are infinite
dimensional an amplitude for every
possible location or for every possible
momentum
so there must be
representations of the rotation group of
this group of rotations which are
infinite dimensional matrices and they
are they are just how what are the
matrices which act on the column vectors
which describe the system that you're
interested in the size of those matrices
will depend on the number of mutually
orthogonal States all right so let's
come
back spin of the electron throw away
everything else out of your head spin of
the electron 2x two matrices the group
elements are the abstract rotations
they're represented by 2 x two
matrices a spin one particle a spin one
particle has three mutually orthogonal
States the rotations are represented by
3x3
matrices in that case those 3x3 matrices
are familiar to some of you they are the
three-dimensional matrices which mix up
the components of three
vectors what comes after spin
uh after three halves right one2 well
first spin zero what about spin
zero spin zero rotations don't act on at
all they just leave it
alone okay so it's completely
trivial you can think of it in some um
very useless sense
that uh that rotations I'm act on a spin
zero just to leave it alone okay that
corresponds to one by one matrices just
the unit Matrix that's all just the unit
Matrix does nothing uh 2 by two that's
spin a half 3x3 that's spin one 4x4
that's spin three halves and so forth so
the same abstract group element the same
abstract symmetry
operation may have many Matrix
representations of different
dimensionality uh that's an important
fact and we're going to we're going to
spend a little more time on
it but let's just uh review for a moment
what
the symmetries we talked about the
symmetries of rotation of
space on a spin on a spin a half
particle in particular on a spin a half
particle uh
and we said those rotation
operations become represented by
matrices which I called
U you because they're
unitary so these are 2x two unitary
matricies I won't bother being more
specific than just putting dots there
those 2x two unitary matrices act on the
state
vectors of a spin a half again I won't
be more specific than writing that let's
erase it for the
moment and this is called a
representation of the
group it's in onetoone correspondence
with the group elements matrix
multiplication group multiplication
there in onet to one
correspondence let's just uh flesh it
out what does it mean for a matrix to be
unitary it means that its inverse is its
permission conjugate
but we know that the number of degrees
of freedom the number of
parameters in a unitary 2x2 matrix is
how many how many did we say there were
eight to begin with four elements each
complex that's four elements this is
four equations that cuts you down to
four but there are only three
independent parameters the three Oiler
angles if you like the three angles
describing a rot the three things
describing a rotation namely the
rotation angle and the two parameters
which determine the direction of the
rotation so there are only three
independent parameters of a rotation
these matrices have one too many
parameters and to get rid of that one
extra parameter one more condition and
that's that the determinant of U
I'll just represent that we could write
it as debt but I'll just write it
as absolute value but it's not really
absolute value it's it's a symbol for
determinant that that is equal to
one now a unitary uh simple fact
incidentally that when you multiply
matrices the determinants
multiply the determinant of a time sorry
the determinant of the product of A and
B is the deter of a Time the determinant
of
B all right uh it is also true that the
determinant of a hermiss conjugate of an
operator is the complex conjugate of the
determinant of the original
operator so here's what we can say let's
take the determinant of both sides of
this the determinant of both sides of
this is first of all the determinant of
UD Daga U but that's also equal to the
determinant of UD
dagger times the determinant of
U and what's the determinant of
one
one is equal to
one uh one here of course means the unit
Matrix all ones on the diagonal all
right now next thing is the determinant
of UD dagger is just the determinant of
um uh
well is the determinant of um is the
complex conjugate of the determinant of
U all right and
um if the determinant of U is one the
determinant of UD dagger is one and the
whole thing is consistent the only point
is that it is consistent it's a
consistent condition on 's that's when I
say consistent I mean that it's
consistent with the law of matrix
multiplication uh if you take a bunch of
unitary matrices every one of which has
determinant one and you multiply them
together you'll again get a thing with
determinant one all right so it's a it's
a mathematical theorem which may not be
too surprising for many of you that the
special unitary matrices 2 x two
matrices which have three parameters in
them special means that UD dag U equals
1 that the group of those matrices is is
identical to the group of uh of
rotations in three-dimensional space now
it's not quite true go
ahead uh is there is there nothing that
says that the determinant has to be
real no the determinant of a it just has
to be radius
one compx number right the determinant
of a unitary Matrix must be a pure
phase okay that's just from the fact
that it's
unitary okay from the fact that it's
unitary but you can take any all right
here's the point you can take any
unitary
Matrix let's suppose its determinant is
e to the I
Theta you can then multiply that unitary
matrix
by um well you'd multiply it by eus I
Theta / 2 because when you calculate the
determin you multiply two elements
together right so if you took U and
multiplied it by eus I Theta /
2 you would construct a special unitary
Matrix all right so the point is um the
extra phase that's in there is almost
trivial you can always get rid of it by
a redefinition of
U and uh in fact the rotation group
doesn't contain this piece here it's
just isomorphic to the matrices with uh
uh with determinant one okay um I told
you a little FIB when I said that su2 is
exactly the same as the rotation groups
it's not exactly there's a 2:1
correspondence instead of a 1:1
correspondence
The unary Operators U and minus U If U
is a unitary operator
UD dagger U equals 1 so is minus U
whatever U Is Right In fact there a 2
to1
correspondence the matrices U and minus
U both correspond to the same rotation
in space but that's a fine point that
that I I which is not going to play any
special role in uh in what we say at
least for the time being
so a
simple state which is almost true is
that uh there's a
correspondence certainly there's a
correspondence but that there's a one:
one correspondence not quite true it's
two to1 correspondence between the
unitary matrices 2 x two matrices the
special unitary matricies those with
determinant one and the
uh the group of
rotations so for that reason the
electron spin or the electron wave fun
function is called a doublet and it's
acted on by 2 x two
matrices now let's talk a little bit
about the generators of a group I think
we actually talked about it but let's uh
be specific about it again the
generators of the group when you have a
symmetry and the Symmetry is represented
by a set of matrices like this then
there's a concept of the generators the
generators have to do with infinitesimal
elements of the group infinite tmal
element of the group means in the case
of rotation a rotation about some axis
by an in by a very very small angle in
other words it's an element of the group
which is very close to Unity unity means
no
transformation Elements which are very
close which are just very small shifts
of angles and so forth are called
infinitesimal elements of the
group and the generators of the group
are very closely related to these
infinitesimally small um uh operations
now one of the reasons that the
infinitely
small elements are important and
interesting is because you can build up
any element out of a sequence of small
ones in other words if I want to rotate
about some angle by a finite rotation I
just think of it as a multiplication of
a bunch of infinite decimal ones so if
if you know the properties of the
infinitesimal generators you can put
together the entire structure of the
group uh we're not going to do that
we're not going to study that today but
we are just going to define the
generators of the group and the reason
we're going to define the generators of
the group because they really are the
conserved quantities they are the
quantities uh that are conserved and
which play the role of conservation laws
once you know what the Symmetry group is
okay so let's define them incidentally
for what I've written here there's
nothing specific to
su2 this could be Su
n where n is the number of elements the
special unitary n byn
matrices they're of course not all
isomorphic to rotations it's only the
su2 group which is isomorphic to
rotations of space su3 su4 su5 not so
easy to
visualize okay so here we have uh the
definition and now let's take an element
which is very close to the
identity it doesn't have to be
su2 let's write it U is equal to the
identity one plus something small and
let's put an i in for for simply
notational simplicity it'll simplify
notations a small parameter
Epsilon and a quantity which is often
I'm not going to call it g g for
generator because we've already used G
for group element and so therefore I
will use T y T beats me I don't
know so U is 1 + i
t what is T let's find out what we can
learn about t we use the fact first of
all that UD dagger U is one all right so
UD dagger U that's 1 + I Epsilon T oh
incidentally it's easy to prove that if
U dagger U is one then u u dagger is one
I won't prove that for you that uh that
um U and U dagger always commute with
each other not not for all operators but
for unitaries so it doesn't matter which
order you multiply all right so it's 1 +
I Epsilon T * 1 - I Epsilon t
dagger if this is U then this is you
dagger I gets changed to minus I when
you complex conjugate and this is
supposed to be equal to
one let's retain things only to the
lowest order in epsilon Epsilon squar is
too small for our interest tonight so
let's just keep things to order Epsilon
and that says 1 * 1 cancels the one
there and it says that I Epsilon * T
minus t dagger is equal to zero or to
simplify it just says that t is equal to
T dagger what's an operator that's equal
to its own
conjugate Herm Mission and Herm Mission
operators in quantum mechanics represent
observables right her Mission operators
represent observable
quantities for the case of
rotations what are these T's what
physical significance do they have there
are three of them first of all why are
there three of them uh there are
actually an infinite number of them but
there are three linearly independent
ones so let me explain why that is the
reason is because the rotation group has
only three
parameters there's only three
independent ways that you can rotate you
can rotate about the x- axis so I could
have made an infinite decimal rotation
about the x-axis I could have made an
infinite decimal rotation about the y
axis or the
z-axis and in fact for an infinite
decimal rotation if I wanted to rotate
about some other axis what I could first
do is rotate a little about the x- axis
and then a little about the Y AIS and
then a little about the z-axis another
way to say it is that the generators
behave like vectors if I want a a vector
in an arbitrary Direction in other words
a vector rotation about some axis about
in a f arbitrary Direction the way I can
think of it is making it up out of the
components the component rotations about
the X Y and z-
axis so there are three
independent directions that you can
rotate in and three independent linearly
independent T's oh we missed one point
come back back up
there is this condition
here the condition that the determinant
is one all right so let me tell you
before get back we'll get back to it in
a moment the determinant being one the
determinant of any Matrix which is of
the form 1 plus let's call it Epsilon
time a small
Matrix the determinant the determinant
of M
is equal to
1 plus Epsilon times the trace of small
M the determinant of a
matrix which is close to the identity is
one that's just the identity and then
the small deviation is Epsilon times the
trace that's something to prove when you
go home and prove that but we can see
what that means immediately
it means that the trace of
T is
zero the trace of T has to be
zero in order for the determinant of U
to be equal to one all right so that's a
second
condition the trace of T is
zero and it should be Herm Mission how
many independent Herm Mission 2x2
matrices are there with Trace equal to
zero the answer is three of them and
they correspond to the rotations about
the three
axes but more abstractly and generally
the generators of the group of
rotations are the angular momentum
operators for a system so that's what
angular momentum means in quantum
mechanics it is the generator the
generators of the rotation group and to
you act with the angular momentum or one
plus I Epsilon time the angular momentum
to rotate a system a small amount and
then if you want to rotate at a large
amount you just do it over and over
again so everything is contained all the
information about the structure of the
group is contained in the
generators right in fact it's contained
in the commutation relations of the
generators those are the important
things I won't go into them again we did
commutation relations of angular
momentum I just wanted to connect things
up a little bit for for you but the
important thing is is that the conserved
quantities associated with the Symmetry
are the
generators and so there are three there
three independent 2 by two uh major se's
say it again there are three independent
2 by two traceless 2 x two Herm Mission
matrices 2 by yeah they have a
name po mat the poly matri no the three
poly matricies and then if you went to
3x3
matrices uh 3x3 unary matrices unary
traceless there are
eight like the Gilman yeah they are
Gilman matri right we're going to do
that in a
moment that eight is the same eight as
the eight
gluons Eightfold
way actually it's a that's a difference
that's actually a different eight not
because it's it's mathematically the
same but it's associated with a
different su3 symmetry than uh than uh
color but yeah mathematics is the
same okay so that
was a little bit
about a a little
review the Sorrows of
Alice Let's uh
let's torture Alice even more let's go
to
su3 right su3 the pattern is exactly the
same except we're we're talking about
3x3
matrices in fact I'm not even sure that
there's very much more to say about it
other than doing some counting and
finding out how many independent
generators there are so to do the
counting it's very easy a 3X3
unitary Matrix has how many
elements how
many starts with
18 18 independent nine independent
complex numbers that's that's 18 but
then we have uh UD dagger U equals
1 now this really is a equation for each
element this is a product this is a
matrix product so we can think of it as
i j and this is i j over here how many
equations is this this is nine equations
so we have 18 - 9 is 9 but then one
additional equation that the determinant
is equal to one that's eight equations
and so we can guess that there are eight
different if we start with a if we start
with the unit Matrix in how many
distinct directions in the group space
can we deform away from the identity and
the answer is eight the implication
being there are eight linearly
independent 3x3 traceless hermiss
matrices traceless Herm Mission matrices
the number of parameters is eight
so
uh and we're going to come back to
[Applause]
that but before we do let's talk a
little bit
about how representations combine to
form new
representations now what we're talking
about here is combining systems
together to form new
systems in the case of spin we might be
talking about combining more than one
particle together to create some sort of
composite for example and that composite
would also have a spin let's not worry
about the motion of the particles let's
just think of them is things that we
staple on top of each other so they nail
down to each other but each one has a
spin so each one has a
spin
uh and let's suppose that we take two
such
particles we put them on top of each
other two half spin particles what do we
get well we get four possible
States but those four possible States
can be thought of as
a um a basis in that four particle
States can be thought of as a spin zero
object and the three spin one objects
that the that a half the two half spins
can make if we take two half spins we
can certainly make a spin one why we can
line up the spins in the same direction
so the Z component of spin can be one it
can be minus one and it can be zero but
it can be zero in two ways all right but
still a spin one particle only has three
states so one of those two ways of
making zero must not be part of the spin
one
multiplet what can it be it can only be
spin zero why spin zero because it
there's nothing for it to transform into
so there are three
combinations which form the spin one
multiplet and one which forms the spin
zero multiplet when you combine spins
together that way there are two possible
total spins you can make so if you were
to take an atom made out of uh made out
of two half spin particles and ignore
the orbital motion Al together one
possibility is that the spins are in the
same direction that would give you spin
one and the other possibility is that
they are in the opposite direction in
which case it would be spin zero it's
Ortho and
parahydrogen particular for the hydrogen
atom where the two spins would be the
proton and the electron
uh right so you combine it's important
to know how to combine spins and to know
what you get what possibilities you get
when you combine them
together what
happens in su3 and we want to jump to
su3 and discuss some very specific
representations of
su3 that the important ones which we
will discuss first of all there is the
triplet the triplet is
simply If U is a 3X3
Matrix then it has to act on a thing
with three
components in the present context the
three components represent the three
colors of a quark so we're talking now
for the moment about one Quark not three
quarks one quark and that Quirk can be
yet red yellow red blue or
green it can be red blue or green this
is the amplitude that it's red this is
the amplitude that it's blue this is the
amplitude that it's
green and what does the group do to them
it mixes them up it mixes up red blue
and green takes any particular State and
sends it to some Quantum superposition
of states of mixed color shall we say so
if we took a red
Quark that would be like an up
spin
001 and we rotated it by this su3
operation we would get something of a
mixed character which would have
amplitudes for being red blue or green
some Quantum superposition so that's
that's the meaning of these
operations but it's interesting and
important to know what happens if you
combine representation together wait let
me go back a step let me go back yeah no
now we want to talk about the various
representations of su3 the
representations of su2 are the spin
States spin zero a half one three halves
two five halves and so forth those are
the representations of
rotations we want to know something
about the representations of su3 and I'm
not going to tell you very much just a
very little bit there are rather two
three important representations for our
purposes one of them is just a
three-dimensional representation and it
can be thought of as the three
components the three things that go here
could be thought of as the three field
operators for let's call them Quark red
Quark blue Quark green we can either
think of these matrices as mixing up the
states of a of a single core or we can
think of it as mixing up the field
operators that create single quarks red
blue and green
right now next this oh this
representation by 3x3 matrices that acts
on the quirks that representation is
called the
three in the same language you would if
you use the same language you would call
the half
spin particle of su2 you would call it
the two two for two
states okay so the three is a
representation that's
identified with the Quark field itself
or with
quarks now there are also
antiquarks
antiquarks their field operators are the
complex conjugates of the Quark
operators so you can ask yourself if
there is a
matrix which acts on Q to give some new
thing we could complex conjugate
everything we could complex conjugate
everything and we could say let's let's
write it if let's call it u u is a 3X3
Matrix if it acts on the column Vector Q
I'm now being a schematic U is a 3X3
Matrix Q is a column Vector if it acts
to give let's call it Q Prime the
rotated Q then what is it that acts on
the complex conjugate or the her Mission
conjugate field
operator that's the object which
represents antiquarks well it's quite
obvious it's going to be the complex
conjugate the uh not the hermiss
conjugate the set of
elements If U is a bunch of
elements then you st is nothing but the
complex conjugate elements call it star
let's call it star to be
consistent so there is a second
representation of
su3 which is the set of matrices which
are the complex conjugate represent
which are the complex conjugate
matrices for every Matrix U there is a
complex conjugate and that defines a
second representation it's called the
complex conjugate
representation it is the transformation
property of
antiquarks and that representation is
called the three bar this is very
abstract but what is it in the case of
electrons what does this correspond to
in the case of
electrons it is simply the fact that if
the electron wave function gets
multiplied by e to the I Theta then the
positron wave function gets multiplied
by E to minus I Theta they transform
with complex conjugate ugate group
elements uh so you would say that the
electron and the positron are complex
conjugate representations of the U1
group that's the language the quark and
the antiquark are complex conjugate
conjugate representations of the group
su3 it would be the complex conjugates
of the PO SP
spines uh for the case su2 yeah now su2
is a special degenerate case where the
Su where the complex conjugate is
equivalent to the original matrices by
another Matrix and it's it's a special
case it's called a real group but uh
this is this is not important for us now
the three and the three bar
representation are quite
different I mean they they look very
similar to each other but they are
distinct they should not be thought of
as the same representation of su3
they're quite
different and in fact the generators the
generators of the three bar
representation are the negatives of the
generators of the three
representation okay that's not too hard
to prove that they uh
they that means they carry the opposite
color if a quirk carries a red color
then an antiquark carries a minus red
color or has the opposite value for the
gener generators all right so these are
the quark and the anti- Quark now what
happens if you take a quark and a quark
two
quirks or a quirk and an anti- Quark
just like you could take two electrons
and make a spin one which was a triplet
not got to do with this three but this
the triplet of su2 just like you can
make a spin one or a spin zero you can
do some similar things with uh with
three and three bar you take two quarks
and put them together you can call that
3 * 3 bar sorry 3 * three two quarks are
three this is just a notation 3 * 3
means two quarks sometimes this is
represented by a circle to indicate that
you're not actually multiplying numbers
You're simply building a space which is
now a space of two quirks it has nine
independent
states red red red blue red green and so
forth all nine
states and if you work out what
representations of su3 appear when you
multiply 3 by
three the answer is first of all there
is an anti- Quark representation that's
going to prove to be
interesting that if you take two
quirks you make something whose color is
the same same as an antiquark that's a
little bit odd don't you think but it's
true it's true anyway and one more
representation called the
six-dimensional representation of su3
we're never going to need the
six-dimensional representation but there
is a six-dimensional representation of
su3 um I can tell you what these things
correspond
to if you think of the quirks as just
indices color indices
then you can combine the two well let's
think about the yeah you combine the two
Quirk States symmetrically or anti-
symmetrically you can combine them
symmetrically or anti- symmetrically
anti- symmetrically gives you the three
bar symmetrically gives you the six but
this is not terribly important point is
if you make two quarks somehow in the
laboratory uh the transformation
properties of the two Quark system under
this su3 there will be one turn ter or
one way of combining them together three
independent states of that system which
will be like an anti- quark and the
other one will be this mysterious six
which we don't give a damn about we'll
see why as we go along now what happens
if we take a quark and an
antiquark if we take an quark and an
antiquark what we get is different than
what we get when we get a quark and a
quark we get again six and three is nine
states but it's not the same nine
possibilities first of all we make an
object which is a one what is a
one that's a thing which is completely
invariant under the color
operations roughly speaking it's a red
plus an anti a red anti- red Quantum
superposition of red anti- red blue
anti-blue and green
anti-green that's one thing and that's a
single representation and it simply does
not
transform under the su3 group it's
called a singlet an su3
singlet and one way of saying it is it's
the analog of combining together two
electrons to make a spin zero State it's
like a spin zero state it does not
transform under the rotation
doesn't transform at all there's just
one state so how could it transform
there's nothing for it to transform into
so when you take a quark and an
antiquark there are nine states one of
which one linear
combination red anti- red plus blue
anti-blue plus green
anti-green that just forms a singlet and
then there are eight others and those
eight others are
called the E dimensional representation
of su3
that eight incidentally think about that
eight for a
moment we've seen eight in another place
it was the number of
generators just like the number of
angular
momenta when you rotate space the
angular momenta rotate into each other
when you rotate in color space the eight
generators get mixed up with each
other the way the eight generators
transform is called the E dimensional
representation of su3 this is sometimes
called the adjoint representation the
words don't matter it's just the
representation that transforms the same
way as the
generators okay and that's what you get
when you multiply three cross three
bar finally one other operation what do
you
get if you take three quarks
Three cross
3 cross 3
you take three quarks there are 27
States well you can do it in pieces you
can say if I combine together these two
quarks what I will get is either a one
sorry is either a three bar which is an
anti- Quark or a
six I when so two of these quirks
together will necessarily
either transform as a
antiquark or as a six a six is UN as a
peculiar representation which I said we
won't care about very much now what
happens if you take this product and now
cross it again with three in other
words we see what we get when we combine
two quarks here's what we get and then
we combine it again with another Quirk
we will either get what appears if we
take a quark and an anti- Quark but we
know what that is that's 1 + 8 the plus
here just means or you either get a one
the singlet or an
eight just like saying you either get
spin one or spin zero that's what this
plus means
or when you multiply 6 *
3 I think you get an 8 plus a
10 but this again is not very
interesting to us we don't care very
much about that the interesting thing
and the most interesting thing is when
we multiply three quarks together we get
the possibility again of a singlet of a
state which is completely colorless it
has no transformation property under the
color it's neutral it's just like taking
a plus charge and a minus charge which
cancel each
other we get the a singlet which has no
su3 transformation at all and it can be
thought of as a combination which simply
is invariant under the su3 group under
the su3 of the mixing up the
quirks what is it can we guess what it
is like I'll tell you what it is it's
just a red a green and a blue
Quark but you have to be careful it's a
red green and blue
Quark anti- symmetrized not important
it's a red green and blue Quark a red
green and blue Quark are the sing are
the singlet then there are other
combinations red red green and so forth
they form the remaining States here but
the most interesting one for our
purposes will be this singlet here so we
see that when we take a quirk and an
antiquark just with regard to the colors
you can combine the colors in a
particular way to get a singlet plus
other stuff and when you take three
quarks you can combine them together to
get a singlet plus other
junk excuse me is it the probability of
these other things so low that we don't
consider it or is reason the question is
what the energy of them is okay and I
will tell you the energy of them is
infinite but we will come to that right
the energy of them is infinite and so
they don't appear in the uh in the
Spectrum now how can the energy of them
be infinite and that's that was a great
puzzle which we Now understand and I'm
going to talk about it a little
bit all right right but
now ah there is one other kind of
particle in nature in sorry there's many
other kinds of particles in nature but
there's one other particle in Quantum
chromodynamics we're talking about
Quantum chromodynamics qcd the theory of
quirks and gluons what of course we've
left out is the gluon
the gluon is an object which I think
I've told you before behaves as if it
were a quark and an anti- Quark with
respect to the Symmetry it doesn't
behave like a quark and an anti- Quark
uh with respect to what happens if you
hid it or anything just with respect to
the color symmetry its color properties
are the same as a quark and an
antiquark but only the eight it
transforms as the eight dimensional
representation it transforms the same
way as the generators of the
group all right so again it is this
octet which is separate from the singlet
here it's the remaining States here and
that's what a gluon is a gluon is a
thing with two indices like a quark and
an anti- quork except a quark and an
antik arranged into this octet of su3 so
it's not neutral
it itself is not
neutral so let's uh
let's
Quirk postulates if you like of quantum
chrom of
qcd it's got an su3 symmetry which I
won't write down the Quark transforms as
a three
sorry the
antiquark transforms as a three
bar and the gluon
or the gluon
field as an
eight course these equations don't
really mean anything particles can't
equal numbers particles are particles
numbers are numbers this just means The
Quirk field transforms as a triplet the
antiquark as the anti- triplet complex
conjugate and the gluon as the eight
which is a piece of a quark
antiquark
this remaining possible gluon doesn't
exist in nature do we know why not
completely uh but the important point
about it is it doesn't mix up with the
other
components and so throwing it away is a
consistent a mathematically consistent
thing to do because it doesn't get mixed
up with the other components when you
transform the su3 group
that's uh
that's group Theory as applied to
Quantum chromodynamics as applied to
quirks and
gluons uh another postulate of quantum
chromodynamics and it's not really a
postulate it's a dynamical output of the
theory but let's take it as a postulate
and then explore what it means in a
moment
uh and that postulate is all of the
particles of nature the real particles
of nature not quark and gluons which are
never seen singly but are always seen in
composits that the particles which can
be separated off and examined
individually can particles of finite
Mass the real things that occur in the
laboratory are all particles real
particles I don't know there's nothing
not real about a quirk so I hate to call
them the real particles the unconfined
particles the free particles
the liberated particles or whatever we
wish to call them free particles are
always transforming
under the one in other words they are
singlets all the real particles in
nature are singlets there is only two
independent ways well I'll tell you what
the ways of creating singlets are this
is mathematical fact now there are only
two fundamental ways of making singlets
out of
quarks one of them is to take a quark
and an anti- quark
all right that creates a singlet the
other is to take three
quarks now you can do other things you
can take a quark and an anti- quark and
just depose it with three
quarks but the elements the basic or you
can take three quarks and another three
quarks three quarks in a singlet and
three other quarks in a singlet that
will also be in a singlet but all of the
objects that you can make up have the
quantum numbers of
combinations of things made out of three
quarks or a quark and an
antiquark what about what about the
gluons themselves oh first of all before
we do that let's give these things names
what is an object made out of three
quirks or a barion a barion right
Baron they always
have half Spin and half spin when I say
half spin that can be one half three 5
halv S halves why because they're made
out of three half spin
particles what about the Quark
antiquarks this is these are the ones of
course in the
three in 3 cross 3 cross three there's
uh the uh the triplet sorry the singlet
are called Barons the singlet in Three
cross three bar what are they called
quark and an
antiquark bons
now we left out one
thing can we make things out of the
gluons can we make things out of the
gluons yeah there is a thing that you
can make just out of
gluons in fact if you take an eight
cross an8 I told you roughly what uh
happens if you combine quarks together
you could ask what happens if you
combine gluons together or gluons with
quirks I'm not going to go through the
whole list of multipli a tables that you
get when you combine all sorts of things
but there's certainly at least one more
interesting thing and that's an eight
cross an8 this is simply two
gluons two gluons now it's not obvious
you get 63 States Al together 8 cross
8 one of them is a
singlet what did I say 63 64 states did
I say 63 yeah there are 64 States in 8
cross 8 and the rest of them form 63
things which are a combination of uh of
uh eights and other things eight appears
a number of times I forget which I don't
remember which representations appear
but there are 63 other states none of
them are singlets just one way of
combining together
gluons to form
singlets so you might ask is there a
part particle which is composed of two
gluons just two gluons bound together
into an su3 singlet and the answer is
yes they're called glue
balls they're not made of quarks they
don't have any Quark content in
them uh they're fundamentally just a
pair of gluons you can also make three
gluons incidentally it's possible also
in it's also possible to get uh more
complicated things but there are glue
balls
so the spectrum of hadrons the spectrum
of strongly interacting particles which
come from quarks and gluons consist of
Barons mesons and glue
balls all of them are color singlets
color singlets is the watch
word
now another fact another fact you can
check this yourself easily I think we've
actually checked it before remember now
all we can make is Quark anti- Quark
Quark Quark Quark or gluon gluon and
combinations of those what kind of
electric charges do we get if we combine
three
quarks
well I think we can get spin I think we
can get charge two Let's see we can get
uh zero one and two
we can get two by taking two three up
quirks three down quirks sorry what was
three down Quirk uh three down quarks is
minus
one three down quarks is minus one and
you have minus one 0 1 and two but the
important point is you cannot make a
fractional charge with three quarks
there's no way to take three quarks and
make a fractional
charge what about a quark and an
antiquark well again you can take an
up an anti- up or uh 2/3 and minus A3 no
2/3 and 1/3 you know you know what the
story is and you can again make integer
charges I don't remember you're telling
us what the charge strange it's the same
as the charges down I did tell you
because the way that I grouped
them yeah it's the same as a down all of
the quirks are either up likee or down
like and they come in three families the
up to
down the charm the strange and the top
and the bottom but they're three
replicas of the same thing so all you
can make is integer charged particles
and so from the point of view of
color the fact that you only have
integer charged particles in nature is
the same statement as all the particles
combine always into su3 singlets and
color
singlets question about that is that a
singlet is like like a pair of Tangled
electrons is that any significance here
yeah other than the way you transform
them
or well that is the way you make such
States is to entangle them very
definitely they are certainly entangled
does it have any uh I'm not sure if you
can't separate separately
well
if you can't separate them because they
get stuck together but uh but you know
you can separate them as far as you like
and uh it'll just cost you a lot of
energy so in principle yes they're
entangled uh entangled
objects not easy to manipulate you
wouldn't want to try to do an experiment
of that type with
them
question uh I'm actually having trouble
understanding those equations
not the details of how you get it but
what what the operations are so the left
hand side got three cross three yeah
which is the group
three grou the representation
three okay so let's let me let me tell
you more mathematically what is going on
here that's sort of my question yeah
okay let's take su2 first all right and
take two spinner
Hales we can think of the two spinner
halves in terms of the field operators
which create their particles that's the
easiest way to think about it for the
moment all right so let's just call the
field operator sigh and there are two
components to it the Sigh which creates
a up Spin and the Sigh which creates a
down spin let's call them s uh s i where
I can take on two values either up or
down okay now supposing we want to
create two
particles if s creates a particle or S
dagger doesn't matter if s creates a
particle how do we create two s creates
a particle we can think of the two
components we can think of it as S one
and S two or S up and S
down and the su2 operations act on this
now that's one particle how do we make
two particles well we act twice with
s but we can act with sigh up twice that
creates two up particles we can act with
s down twice that creates two down
particles or we can uh do it uh one of
each so let's write s i s
j in fact these two operators don't
really have to correspond to the same
part iCal let's even uh we could even
think of one of them as being the
electron the other being the proton in a
hydrogen atom for example let's see
let's even give them different
names uh s and fi they might be the same
they might not be but let's uh let's
allow them to be different for the
moment okay so this now is an object
with two indices it's an object with two
indices it's kind of like a tensor if we
were thinking about vectors in
three-dimensional space
tensors are objects with two Vector
indices this object is like a
tensor in that it has repeated
indices now su2 can operate on it
because su2 operates on S and it acts on
fi this is a collection of four objects
up up up down down up and down down so
we could lay out those four
sigh up sigh up sorry f
up sigh up fi down and so forth and so
on we could lay them out in an array and
then ask what happens when you act with
su2 on this composite object here well
they get mixed up with each other they
get mixed up with each other for the
simple reason that the size get mixed up
with each other and the fs get mixed up
with each
other and so certainly these side time
FS are going to get mixed up with each
other and there's going to be a 4x4
Matrix which represents the same
action as just going through size and
F's separately and rotating them by the
group
action okay now you look at these at the
way these things mix up with each other
you look at the way they mix up with
each other and you come to a discovery
you discover that the
combination let's see what it is s up F
down minus s down f
up doesn't mix with anything else under
this operation it just goes into
itself it just goes into itself this is
an easy thing to check you just see how
su2 acts on S up it mixes it with s down
you see how it acts on five down and you
check what happens to this particular
combination and the answer is nothing so
this is a
singlet this is one the other three
possibilities what are they they are s
up F down plus side down f up this is a
I have not put in square roots of two
but you could put in the square roots of
two if you wanted
this is orthogonal to
this and then there's s up fi
up and S down F
down what happens when you do the su3
su2 rotations on these states they mix
into each
other in particular ways they will mix
into each other this
singlet does not get mixed with these
three states at all and these three
states mix up among themselves as if
they were a spin one
object they get mixed among each other
and this is then called the
three spin one has three
states these three mix up among
themselves this doesn't mix up with
anything so when you combine two half
spin States that's uh well
when you combine two half spin States
you make a one or you make a three
depending on which combination you take
you make a one or you make a three you
make spin one sorry you make spin zero
or spin
one that's the sense in which these
equations are being used here
um when you combine together a quk and
an antiquark there are nine different
ways to do it one of the linear
combinations behaves in this way
here and it's a singlet and the others
transform into each other eight objects
eight additional objects would transform
into each other so that's that's the
meaning of these equations here how many
of each kind of combination you
get is that are those is that a unique
thing this multiplication couldn't be 2
+ 7 if the say it again okay so you have
to know
3 couldn't be 2 + 7 or no no you you
have to know what the representations of
su3 are we did a bit of work to find out
what the representations of su2 were and
they were all the spin half and spin and
integer spin particles we could spend
two more weeks studying su3 and find out
what the representations of su3 are what
are what Matrix representations are
there not there are not Matrix
representations of every dimension
ity there are Matrix representations for
su2 there happen to be for every
dimensionality a matrix representation
of su2 for su3 not so there's the
singlet there's the there's the triplet
there's the anti- triplet there is the
uh octet the eight there's a 10 there's
a 15 there's a 20 there's a whole bunch
of them but not every number appears in
the possible matrices which have the
same multiplication table as su3 so
that's that's a bit of work to prove we
didn't want to go there I just went
there by saying all right here's what
you
get and uh but the but the real
interesting point is the singlets that
appear the ways that you can combine
quirks together to get combinations
which don't rotate or which are the
analog of electrically neutral why do I
say electrically neutral because
electrically neutral are exactly the
objects which don't transform under that
U1
the things which the phase cancels out
of remember go back
again uh to
electrodynamics the things which are
electrically neutral are the
combinations where all the phases cancel
out if an electron has an e to the I
Theta and a positron an e to the minus I
Theta then an electron and a positron
the combination of them are neutral
don't transform at all two electrons
that gets an e to 2 I Theta so it's not
called neutral or it's not called or or
transforms under the group so singlets
are important but you should just think
of them as neutral objects with respect
to the uh to the transformation
properties and
uh I mean is there a possibility that
you could just show with that single uh
that that transformation uh just one
example there is that the oh we can go
through it yeah uh maybe it's too much
it is a little too much but
um
yeah uh all right one simple way to see
it I don't know if this will help you at
all uh if we write just write this
object here Epsilon you know what
Epsilon I
is an it's the 2x two Matrix which is
the anti- symmetric
Matrix yeah um and contract the indices
this way it's that that's equal to this
that's equal to this and it's easy to
prove that this is a oh okay
this I'll just spend a moment at it in
every dimensionality for matri Matrix
dimensionality there is always an
Epsilon symbol which has a certain
number of indices for 2x two matrices
the Epsilon symbol and the Epsilon
symbol is the anti-symmetric uh the
fully anti-symmetric Matrix composed out
of zeros and
ones okay all right Epsilon i j is the
2x two Matrix what about for what about
for 3x3 matrices in a
three-dimensional and it's Epsilon K
requires three indices all right so I'll
tell you right now if you take an su3
Epsilon i j k and let's call it what did
we call the Quirk fields Q Qi QJ
qk then you
make the three qu
singlet which has no color i j and k
have to all be different from each other
otherwise this is zero so that's why I
said a red a green and a
blue uh make a singlet okay uh I we
don't want to make Alice suffer too much
tonight um for what is worth I just
happened to bump into this in this other
book uh that 8 cross 8 equal 27 oh let's
write it down okay 8+
8 all right so that means when you when
you take two eights and put them
together in other words two gluons you
first of all make a
singlet what else plus 8 plus 8 plus 10
well say it again 8 plus 8 plus 8 okay
I'll tell you what this means in a
minute 10 10 plus 10 plus 10
okay all right so let's see is that
right uh 10 and 10 is 20 and 8 and 8
this should make
uh what who who 8 * 8 is
64 oh it's plus 27 it's not equal equal
yeah it's plus 27 at the end you say
there's a plus of 27 yeah does that make
63 I can't
tell 64 is that
64 yeah okay good all right all right
so for your information this is a fact I
know I know the representations of su3
up to 27 I after I think there's a 35
but I don't
remember uh but 10 another
10 uh we don't have we're not up to 6 no
okay all right so what this means is
first of all there is one and only one
combination Quantum Quantum
superposition of states of two gluons
which makes a singlet one and only one
and that's the glue ball then it turns
out there are two orthogonal ways of
making
octets
two that's 16 States Al together but
they form two groups and the first group
mixes into themselves without mixing
into the second the second group mixes
into itself without mixing into the
first and both of them form octets
different combinations different
patterns of imry of the wave function of
the of the State uh of the two of the
two um uh gluon system then there's
something called a
10 and again there are two distinct ways
of combining the gluons together to make
tens but who cares about tens because
they don't appear in nature anyway and
then there's a 27 dimensional
representation how about 3 cross 3 cross
3 I don't okay so there's a singlet
I don't know I don't we had them written
down but I don't
remember can I ask question is it fair
to say that that what happens if you
change the sort of the basis of the of
the thing to the let's go back to the
the spin two case to the to the singlet
and the triplet and the two up up up
down down where we going where are we
yeah so you have that and so so use
those four things as as a basis then the
Matrix which describes the operation
factors into
a has has uh has one z0 Z and then a
a let's see yes and a and a and a lower
part that is that move that moves the
that exchange moves the three among
themselves so the make you can describe
it in terms of how how the Matrix looks
if you just work in terms of the basis
vectors up up up down up up up up down
down up and down down then there's a
certain set of four 4x4 matrices which
represent the group right but if you
work in terms of these linear
combinations this one this one this one
and this one then the
matrices have exactly the property that
you say there's a one over here and then
3x3 matrices down here right and the
same thing for this other case here
there's a
one that's right that's right the
matrices the big eight the big 64x 64
dimensional matrices break up into a
bunch of
blocks blal it's block diagonal in a
particular basis in the basis in the
basis that's right that's right that's
right in fact what what you're saying is
that there that there exists a basis
exactly in which
in which this complicated Matrix
simplifies into black diagonal that's
right so there are 64
States so the su3 operation has to be
represented on the two on the two gluon
system as 64x 64 dimensional matrices
right but in some basis those 64 by 64
dimensional matrices are a one an 8x8
Matrix over here another 8x8 Matrix over
here then a 10x10 M I don't have enough
room another 10x10 Matrix and then a 27
Matrix down there in a particular basis
that's exactly
right so each one of those doesn't mix
the other ones that's right
each that's right in the right bases
they don't get mixed this one doesn't
get mixed with this one doesn't get
mixed with this one they only get mixed
together as an 8 dimensional repes
is there is there a label or name for
that type
of subset of the total mat toal that
basis
uh you mean for this uh for a piece of
it like
this
um uh well when you
multi I'm not I'm not sure what the what
the right right buzz
word I think you're looking for a
particular term which escaping me right
now uh in fact I don't think such a term
exists but I know what you mean
um uh when you say that when you say
particles uh the 10 particles don't
exist in nature and and the other say
you you declared don't exist in nature
so we don't have to care well maybe you
shouldn't say you shouldn't care about
them but they won't appear as real
particles in the laboratory
we're going to talk about what uh What
uh creates this peculiar situation that
you can't have a free Quark by itself
but we'll come to
that so let's talk about it a little
bit incidentally the quantum
chromodynamics idea goes back a long
ways it goes back
some I know who was it's due to nambo
the yiro nambo and um nambo had the idea
quite quite 1962 quite maybe good 10
years before uh Quantum chromodynamics
became the standard theory of uh of
quirks and
gluons in fact the whole idea of color
goes back to him he didn't call it color
I don't know what he called it and the
idea of gluons also in the same idea and
his idea was fairly simple he understood
that if you made color
singlets then you would not get
fractionally charged particles that was
his motivation what do you have to add
into Quantum chrom into the theory of
quirks in order to have some Dynamics
which will forbid particles of
fractional charge so he realized that if
the quirks carried this kind of color
quantum number and if the color always
had to be a
singlet then you would never get uh you
would never get uh fraction Ally charged
particles uh he had an answer to the
question of why particles should only
occur in singlets and it went something
like this he
said all right now we now we need
another postulate and the other
postulate is the connection or the
interaction between quirks and
gluons the postulate is that gluons play
the same role in quantum
chromodynamics that photons do in
electrodynamics but photons couple to
the electric charge the source of the
photon field is electric charge the
gluons there are eight of
them what are the sources of the gluons
what is the source of a gluon it must
there must be eight quantities eight
conserved
quantities which you can think of as
being similar to charge and each one of
them is a source of that particular
gluon of that particular species of
gluon the eight the eight
gluons correspond to fields which are
similar in some sense to uh uh to uh the
photons or to the electromagnetic field
the electromagnetic field is sourced by
electric charge what is the source of
the gluon field well what eight
quantities do we have available the
eight generators of
su3 which are analogous to angular
momentum for
su2 angular momentum is a conserved
quantity it's additive if you have two
objects you add their angular
momentum uh and color really means when
you speak of the color of an object
you're speaking about how it transforms
under the group but the actual thing
which radiates the thing which radiates
the gluon field is the color itself or
the color itself or the generators of
the Color Group eight of them and each
one can
emit the appropriate kind of
gluon the first meaning of this is that
if you take a colored object such as a
quark it's going to be surrounded by a
Glon field
so much like
electrodynamics
uh
the quantum
chromodynamics replaces the
electromagnetic field with a Quantum
Chromo with a chromodynamic field but
the only thing new about it is that
there are eight such fields and the
eight such Fields transform the same way
under that same eight that's associated
with the
gluons okay so that's the first
thing now the second thing is to know
something about uh about the Dynamics of
elect
electromagnetism let's begin with a
charge and an anti-
charge a charge and an anti-
charge attract each other the meaning of
that is that if you bring them close
together the energy goes
down right so a char and anti- charge
have less energy if they're close
together than they are than if they're
far apart that's why they bind that's
why they bind because the energy of a
neutral system is less than the energy
of the two charge well the energy of a
neutral system is lower than the energy
of a charge system as a rule for example
the energy of 2 plus charges is much
more than the energy of a plus charge
and a minus charge how do I know that
because the two plus charges repell each
other you have to do work to push the
two plus charges together you get work
out of uh out of letting a plus charge
fall towards a minus charge so here's an
example where a system with a net charge
has more energy than a system in which
the charges cancel out another way to
think about it is if you have two plus
charges the lines of force have to go
somewhere
and so there's net field out beyond the
object that net field has field
energy field energy is always positive
it's proportional to the square of the
electric field and so there's field
energy stored in the fact that there are
two plus charges here if there was a
plus charge and a minus charge they
might be fielded in in between them and
let's suppose you brought them very
close together there might be a little
dipole field in there but there would be
no field on the outside there would be
no large field energy on the outside and
so the field energy or the field energy
stored in a neutral system is less than
the field energy stored in a uh in a
charge system the the larger the charge
of the
electron the more profitable it is let's
say to have a neutral system
energetically or the less profitable or
the more EXP expensive it is in energy
to have a net charge system just the
bigger the electric charge if we had if
the electric charge of the electron was
a thousand times bigger than it is the
self energy of the electron due to the
electromagnetic field would be much
bigger than it is in fact the repulsive
force between two plus charges would be
much much stronger than it is and the
amount of energy it would take to
assemble two plus charges would be very
much bigger than the energy needed for a
plus charge and a minus charge the huge
charge of the electron would then make
it very very uh prohibitive to have net
charge and very very efficient low
energy to have all charges cancel
out so if the coupling constant of
electrodynamics were large very large we
would be very used to the idea that the
low energy particles the low mass mass
is energy of course the low mass
particle in nature the low mass objects
in nature would be electrically
neutral if the charge was big enough we
might never have discovered individual
electrically charged particles they
would be confined it would just be too
prohibitive and energy to pull them out
of an atom for example so what nambo
said is look if I have this Quantum
chromodynamics and if color the color
generator or the color degree of freedom
is the source of the gluon field then if
we make the charge the numerical
coupling
constant the uh the analog of electric
charge if we make it large enough then
it will be simply impossible to pull
apart these quirks into non- singlet
States a singlet state is the analog of
neutral pulling them apart you would be
left over with net amounts of color
which would cost you lots of energy so
he understood that when systems
were in the color singlet State they
were fully attractive and pull
themselves together when they weren't
there was always an element of repulsion
that uh that meant it cost an enormous
amount of energy to pull them together
so that was nbo's explanation he said
Quantum chromodynamics has a natural way
of making sure that the real particles
in nature are integer charged
and that quarks always come in either
the Quark anti- Quark combination or the
three Quark
combination uh and this was essentially
correct it turned out to
be correct but the Dynamics is a little
more interesting than that so let's talk
about the Dynamics and why the Dynamics
is more
interesting any questions up till
now okay why is the Dynamics more
interesting than that and the reason the
Dynamics is more interesting than that
is because the analog of the photon the
gluon is charged carries
color it the gluon itself is not neutral
with respect to the remember the neutral
piece was this ninth member that we
threw away the eight gluons themselves
are
not neutral they transform under the
eight
it's as if they had a color charge that
is why gluons don't appear in nature uh
as objects the color they they
themselves are colored and because
they're colored they have a big color
field around them and they are
prohibitive in energy but this is
interesting what it says is that the
gluon itself is charged in a way that
the photon is not the fact that photons
are not
charged means they don't interact with
each other they're not sources are a
photon is not a source of another
Photon electrodynamics or at least
classical electrodynamics is a
completely linear theory meaning to say
that uh that electromagnetic waves just
pass right through each
other that's because the electromagnetic
wave itself is not charged and doesn't
uh doesn't influence other
electromagnetic waves
so electrodynamics the photon and the
electromagnetic wave are very simple Le
and linear but in Quantum chromodynamics
it's much more complicated the analog of
the photon itself is charged that means
that the analog of an electromagnetic
wave intersecting another
electromagnetic wave will be a serious
interacting phenomenon in fact even just
a single wave of the gluon one part of
it will interact with the other one part
of it may have some color the other part
of it may have some color those colors
will interact with each other and the
Dynamics of gluons is far and the and
the Not Just gluons but the
field analogous to the electromagnetic
the Maxwell field is far far more
complicated and
dynamically interesting but also much
more difficult to
understand turned out that
the pretty much the important important
thing that happens which is
new can be summarized fairly
easily and I'll summarize it for you on
the Blackboard in terms of pictures the
equations that go with this there are
equations but uh but the pictures I
think are better than the
equations there's a quirk and there and
there is its Quantum chromodynamic gluon
field around it
now in electrodynamics the different
pieces of the photon field or the
electromagnetic field do not interact
with each other and so there's no sense
in which one field line repels or
attracts other field lines they just uh
they're just completely independent they
don't interact with each other in
Quantum chromodynamics the gluon field
itself is not neutral and therefore the
gluon field interacts with other pieces
of gluon field and the result is very
simple it turns out to be fairly simple
the lines of flux basically attract each
other they attract each other and they
attract each other in a
way which
makes the rule about lines of flux is
they don't end except on another
charge the lines of flux coming out of a
quirk or coming out of a color charge
attract each
other and in the process of attracting
each other energetically they want to
Form Tubes they want to Form Tubes of
flux with a flux running right down the
tube it is more or less you can either
imagine that the lines of flux are
attracting each other or that empty
space is repelling the lines of flux and
pushing them and squeezing them into a
tube that's what happens that's pretty
much the main effect of the nonlinear
interactions between the gluon field
that that it makes it
energetically
favorable to take those lines of flux
and bundle them and bundle them into
tubes let's suppose that's true now now
supposing we have a quark and an
antiquark we have a quark and an anti-
Quark lines of flux come out of the
quark and go into the
antiquark if this were
electrodynamics those lines of flux
would separate and form the
nice dipole pattern that we're all
familiar with anybody who's ever looked
at a magnet and
right all
right the field energy associated with
this big dipole configuration is
relatively small because the field gets
weak far
away in this configuration there's a
uniform field no matter how far you take
these particles from each other there is
a uniform field in
between just exactly as if you took an
electro electric or magnetic field and
pushed it through a tube there would be
a uniform field the lines of flux don't
end and because there's a uniform field
there's a uniform energy per unit
length what's the result of that the
result of that is if you try to separate
a quirk from an
antiquark the energy just grows linear
ly with the distance between them as you
pull this out it's like uh the gluon
field was really sticky really uh
Turkish taffy except Turkish taffy would
get thinner and thinner as you stretched
it out huh so it's not quite like
chewing gum with Turkish taffy it's like
a kind of chewing gum that as you
separated it always created more chewing
gum in between so that it never got
thinner and thinner there's always a
fixed number of lines of flux coming out
of every charged object
and they don't disappear so this tube
it's called a flux
tube or
fluxoid and the fluxoid has a uniform
charge per unit uh um
distance any charged object which means
any object with nonzero color any non
singlet any object which is not a
singlet here it is it puts out lines of
flux
those lines of flux bundle themselves
and unless they are unless they end on
an object of opposite
color that object is just going to have
an infinite charge because those lines
of flux have to go someplace they'll end
at Infinity the cost and energy will be
infinite that's the basic dynamics of
quantum
chromodynamics linear flux tubes like
this which are the ingredients which
keep quirks from flying around freely
if you hit a quark real hard inside a
Meson this is a picture of a uh sort of
extreme picture of a Meson a quark and
an antiquark you hit that Quark hard it
goes flying out but it simply can't get
away the field energy just increases and
increases and increases linearly with
distance until you've run out of kinetic
energy and then it gets pulled back or
something else happens what's the other
thing that can happen
right yeah right the other thing that
can happen is that the string can break
if this is a
quark and this is an
antiquark
then spontaneously out of the vacuum
particle pair production can create an
antiquark over here and a quirk over
here but you still have haven't created
a quirk you've created two
mesons so you give one quirk in a Meson
a good good shot you hit it really hard
it tries to escape and either it can't
escape because it runs out of energy and
gets pulled
back but actually more likely what will
happen is a quirk and an anti- quork
will be created in between and you'll
just create
tons if this Quirk over here is still
going too fast it may still try to
escape it may try to escape this one
over here what will
happen and so what happens when you hit
a quk really hard is that inside a Meson
is that a whole bunch of mesons go
flying off forming what is called a jet
you ever get any others oh yeah oh yes
absolutely you can get anything as long
as it's
neutral right this is the picture of a
Meson the other ingredient that is in
Quantum
chromodynamics is that three quarks can
exist this doesn't explain three quarks
the three quarks are explained by a
mathematical fact that the flux lines
can come together in
threes Quark Quark
quark and
uh but that it's not too surprising
because three quirks again make a
neutral object three quirks again make a
neutral object and that means that if
you have three quarks there'll be no net
lines coming out of it so somehow the
lines of force that come out of each one
of them have to be able to cancel each
other that's Quantum chromodynamics it's
based on the su3 group and it's called a
gauge Theory a gauge theory is simply
any Theory where the conserved
quantities are coupled to a Maxwell like
field are coupled to a field similar to
photons it has a deeper meaning than
that but for our purposes anytime there
is a conserved quantity analogous to
electric charge which functions as the
source of a photonik
field Photon like field gluon like field
that's called a gauge Theory the gauge
theories are always B based on
symmetries why are they based on
symmetries because they're based on the
idea of conserved
charge and conserved charge means a
symmetry of some kind
incidentally why what's the connection
between conservation and lines of
flux conservation and lines of flux are
intimately
connected
um if you have a
rule for examp example in
electrodynamics that every charged
particle has to be the source of lines
of
flux and that lines of flux can only end
on charged particles then charge has to
be conserved there's no way remember
these lines of force go off to Infinity
well you could say I could make this
charge suddenly disappear if I allow the
lines of flux to simultaneously all
disappear but that would violate the
speed of light constraint you would be
able to send a message arbitrarily far
distance if by simply removing that
charge you
suddenly change the field at
Infinity the fact that you cannot send a
signal faster than the speed of light
tells you that you can't remove this
charge why because it's sort of anchored
by the flux lines at infinity and if you
could remove it
either one of two things either you
would send a sudden signal far away that
the charge wasn't there by removing the
field or you would be left over with
these lines of flux that don't end on
charges so if lines of flux have to end
on charges then that's T amount to
saying that the sources of the field are
conserved which in another language says
there must be a
symmetry so some symmetries are
connected did with Photon like fields
which give rise to lines of flux those
theories are called gauge theories okay
and you can't even imagine without
breaking the rules of a theory what it
would mean for the charge not be
conserved because the rules of the
theory attach the charged particles to
the uh to the lines of for of
force okay that's that's Quantum
chromodynamics now we've actually gone
either depending on how you count either
2/3 or 3/4 of the way through the
standard
model we've gone through nine generators
if you like the eight generators of su3
and what's the other
one the electric charge the electric
charge which is not the ninth generator
of u3 the electric charge those are nine
conserved quantities they coupled to the
nine gauge Fields the eight gluons and
the photon
the standard model has three more
generators which we will talk about so
that's we've got nine out of 12 that's
3/4 uh the other way of camping is to
say we studied
su3 that's Quantum Chromo Dynamics we've
studied U1 that's
electrodynamics the standard model is
su3 cross su2 cross1 we're missing the
su2 the su2 not it's not angular
momentum there's another ingredient in
the standard model called su2 we'll take
up we'll start to take up su2 next time
we've covered a lot of
ground and um I think in about two more
lectures we can probably finish off the
basic structure of the standard model
su3 cross su2 cross U1 put it together
into a
package and
um and I think the other element that we
need of course is the higs field the
higs field plays an important role
there
uh but um I would say within about three
lectures we will have the working parts
of the standard
model and then we can start to explore
what the puzzles of it are why uh why
people think we have to go beyond the
standard model and why people think
there are going to be interesting new
things discovered at CERN I think that's
where we want to get and uh
okay
good for more please visit us at
stanford.edu